So I'm here to tell you a story of success from Africa.
أذن، أنا هنا لأخبركم عن قصة نجاح من أفريقيا
A year and a half ago,
قبل سنة ونصف
four of the five people who are full time members
أربعة من الخمسة أعضاء المداومين بإستمرار
at Ushahidi,
في أوشاهيدي
which means "testimony" in Swahili,
التي تعني "شهادة" في اللغة السواحلية
were TED Fellows.
كانوا مشاركين في تيد
A year ago in Kenya we had post-election violence.
قبل عام في كينيا شهدنا أحداث عنف عقب الإنتخابات
And in that time we prototyped and built,
في ذلك الوقت صممنا وبنينا
in about three days, a system that would allow
في حوالي ثلاثة أيام، نظام يسمح
anybody with a mobile phone
لأي شخص لديه هاتف محمول
to send in information and reports on what was happening around them.
بإرسال معلومات وتقارير حول ما يجري حولهم
We took what we knew about Africa,
أستخدمنا ما عرفناه عن أفريقيا
the default device,
الجهاز التلقائي
the mobile phone, as our common denominator,
الهاتف المحمول، كقاسم مشترك بيننا
and went from there.
وبدأنا من هناك
We got reports like this.
أستقبلنا تقارير مثل هذا
This is just a couple of them from January 17th, last year.
هذه بعضها منذ 17 يناير، العام الماضي
And our system was rudimentary. It was very basic.
وكان نظامنا بدائياً. هذا شئ أساسي
It was a mash-up that used data that we collected from people,
كان مزيجاً من البيانات التي جمعناها من الناس
and we put it on our map.
والتي وضعناها على الخريطة
But then we decided we needed to do something more.
لكن قررنا أننا نحتاج الى فعل المزيد
We needed to take what we had built
أحتجنا أخذ ما بنيناه
and create a platform out of it so that it could be used elsewhere in the world.
ونصنع منه منصة يمكن إستخدامها في أماكن أخرى في العالم
And so there is a team of developers
ولذا هناك فريق من المطورين
from all over Africa, who are part of this team now --
من كل انحاء أفريقيا، يشاركون في فريق العمل الآن
from Ghana, from Malawi, from Kenya.
من غانا، من ملاوي، من كينيا
There is even some from the U.S.
حتى أن بعضهم من أمريكا
We're building for smartphones, so that it can be used in the developed world,
نحن نطوّر هواتف ذكية، يمكن إستخدامها في العالم المتطور
as well as the developing world.
بنفس القدر في العالم النامي
We are realizing that this is true.
نعتقد أن هذه حقيقة
If it works in Africa then it will work anywhere.
اذا نجحت في أفريقيا فستنجح في أي مكان آخر
And so we build for it in Africa first
لذا فقد طوّرناها في أفريقيا أولاً
and then we move to the edges.
وبعدها ننتقل الى أماكن أخرى
It's now been deployed in the Democratic Republic of the Congo.
الآن تعمل في جمهورية الكونغو الديموقراطية
It's being used by NGOs all over East Africa,
وتستخدمها المنظمات الطوعية في كل شرق أفريقيا
small NGOs doing their own little projects.
المنظمات الطوعية الصغيرة تعمل في المشاريع الخاصة بها
Just this last month it was deployed by
في الشهر الماضي فقط أستخدمتها
Al Jazeera in Gaza.
قناة الجزيرة في غزة
But that's actually not what I'm here to talk about.
لكن ليس هذا ما جئت للحديث عنه
I'm here to talk about the next big thing,
أنا هنا لأتحدث عن الخطوة الكبيرة القادمة
because what we're finding out is that
لأن ما نكتشفه هو
we have this capacity to report
أن لدينا المقدرة على الإبلاغ
eyewitness accounts of what's going on in real time.
من شهود عيان على الحدث، مباشرةً
We're seeing this in events like Mumbai recently,
رأينا ذلك في أحداث مثل مومباي مؤخراً
where it's so much easier to report now
حيث من السهل جداً إرسال تقرير الآن
than it is to consume it.
بدلاً عن إستهلاكه
There is so much information; what do you do?
هناك كم هائل من المعلومات، ماذا ستفعل؟
This is the Twitter reports for over three days
هذه تقارير تويتر لمدة ثلاث أيام
just covering Mumbai.
تغطي مومباي فقط
How do you decide what is important?
كيف تقرر ما هو مهم؟
What is the veracity level of what you're looking at?
ما مستوى المصداقية في ما تأخذ منه؟
So what we find is that there is this
أذن ما نتوصل اليه هو أن
great deal of wasted crisis information
هناك إهدار لكثير من معلومات الأزمة
because there is just too much information for us to
لأن هناك الكثير من المعلومات المتاحة لنا
actually do anything with right now.
لنفعل بها أي شئ في الوقت الراهن
And what we're actually really concerned with
ما نهتم به في الحقيقة
is this first three hours.
هو الثلاث ساعات الأولى
What we are looking at is the first three hours.
ما نبحث عنه في الثلاث ساعات الأولى
How do we deal with that information that is coming in?
كيف نتعامل مع المعلومات الواردة؟
You can't understand what is actually happening.
لا تستطيع فهم ما يجري بالفعل
On the ground and around the world
على أرض الواقع وحول العالم
people are still curious,
يتوق الناس للمعرفة
and trying to figure out what is going on. But they don't know.
ويحاولون معرفة ما يجري. لكنهم لا يعرفون
So what we built of course, Ushahidi,
لذا ما بنيناه بالفعل، أوشاهيدي
is crowdsourcing this information.
هو حشد مصادر هذه المعلومات
You see this with Twitter, too. You get this information overload.
تشهدون ذلك عبر تويتر، أيضاً. يأتيكم كم هائل من المعلومات
So you've got a lot of information. That's great.
فلديك كميات هائلة من المعلومات، ذلك عظيم
But now what?
لكن ماذا الآن؟
So we think that there is something interesting we can do here.
لذا نعتقد أن هناك شئ مثير يمكننا فعله هنا
And we have a small team who is working on this.
ولدينا فريق عمل صغير يعمل على هذا
We think that we can actually create
نعتقد أن بمقدورنا في الحقيقة صنع
a crowdsourced filter.
مصفاة لحشود المعلومات
Take the crowd and apply them to the information.
يأخذ الحشد ويطبقها على المعلومات
And by rating it and by rating
وبتقييمها وبتقييم
the different people who submit information,
الأشخاص الذين قدموا المعلومات
we can get refined results
يمكننا الحصول على نتائج محسنة
and weighted results.
ونتائج مرجحة
So that we have a better understanding
بذلك نصل الى فهم أفضل
of the probability of something being true or not.
حول إحتمالية أن يكون الشئ صحيحاً أم لا
This is the kind of innovation that is,
هذا النوع من الإبتكار هو
quite frankly -- it's interesting that it's coming from Africa.
بصراحة شديدة-- من المشوق أن يأتي من أفريقيا
It's coming from places that you wouldn't expect.
يأتي من أماكن لا يمكنكم تصورها
From young, smart developers.
من شباب، مطورين أذكياء
And it's a community around it that has decided to build this.
والمجتمع في الجوار الذي قرر تطوريها
So, thank you very much.
لذا ، شكراً جزيلاً لكم
And we are very happy to be part of the TED family.
ونحن سعداء كوننا جزء من أسرة تيد
(Applause)
(تصفيق)